A Finding Aid to the Jock Truman Papers, 1852-2011, in the Archives of American Art AAA.trumjock
Archives of American Art
Jock Truman papers
1852-2011
AAA.trumjock
Archives of American Art
4 Linear feet
The papers of gallery director and art collector Jock Truman measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1852 to 2011. Found within the collection are biographical material; correspondence with friends, family, artists, and others; records of the short-lived Truman Gallery; a few writings by Truman; printed material; artwork by Truman and others; and photographs of Truman, his partner Eric Green, friends, family, and the Truman-Green collection of artwork. A small amount of material documents his work at the Betty Parsons Gallery.
Truman, Jock, 1920-
Arrangement note
This collection is arranged as 7 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, circa 1914-2006 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1929-2011 (0.6 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 3: Truman Gallery Records, 1975-1979 (9 folders; Boxes 2, 6)
Series 4: Writings, circa 1970s-2005 (1 folder; Box 2)
Series 5: Printed Material, 1852, 1940s-2010 (0.5 linear feet; Boxes 2, 6, OV 7)
Series 6: Artwork, 1860-1995 (0.3 linear feet; Boxes 2, 6, OV 7)
Series 7: Photographs, circa 1860s-2009 (1.9 linear feet; Boxes 2-6, OV 7)
Biographical/Historical note
Jock Truman (1920-2011) was an art collector, dealer, and gallery owner in New York, New York. Truman was born in Minneapolis, Minnesota, the son of Curtis Truman and Athelyn Amundsen Truman. He attended the University of Cincinnati from 1938 to 1941 and served in the U.S. Armed Forces in Brazil from 1942 to 1946. From 1946 to 1950 he attended the Harvard Graduate School of Design where he studied with Josef Albers, Gyorgy Kepes, and Hyman Bloom. During the 1950s he owned Thirty-Five River St. Inc., a Boston firm specializing in architectural and interior design.
Truman worked at Robert Isaacson Gallery for four years before moving to Betty Parsons Gallery, where he worked from 1961 to 1974. There he gained specialist knowledge regarding the work of Ad Reinhardt and assisted Reinhardt's widow in the evaluation of artworks after the artist's death. In 1974 he served as director of Parsons Gallery and he and Betty Parsons opened the Parsons-Truman Gallery, which operated as a joint venture from 1975 to 1976. In 1976 he opened Truman Gallery at 38 East 57th St. The gallery closed in 1979.
In 1989 Truman and his companion of over 30 years, Eric Green, moved to Miami. Truman and Green had a large collection of art which they donated to various museums including the Bass Museum of Art and the Museum of Contemporary Art in North Miami.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to Archives' Washington D.C. center. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The collection was donated in 1982 and 2005-2006 by Jock Truman and 2011 by Truman via Eric Kane, Executor.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of gallery director and art collector Jock Truman measure 4.0 linear feet and date from 1852 to 2011. Found within the collection are biographical material; correspondence with friends, family, artists, and others; records of the short-lived Truman Gallery; a few writings by Truman; printed material; artwork by Truman and others; and photographs of Truman, his partner Eric Green, friends, family, and the Truman-Green collection of artwork. A small amount of material documents his work at the Betty Parsons Gallery.
Betty Parsons Gallery.; Green, Eric; Truman Gallery.; Art dealers--New York (State)--New York; Art--Collectors and collecting--New York (State)--New York; Gallery directors--New York (State)--New York; Photographs
- Biographical Material, circa 1914-2006; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1; Truman, Jock, 1920-
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical material includes biographical summaries about Truman, various identification documents, school and military records, award certificates, and genealogy records on the Truman family. Also found are family records belonging to Truman's partner, Eric Green. Additionally there are records of the donation of a large portion of their art collection to the Bass Museum of Art and Museum of Contemporary Art in North Miami.
  - Address Books, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Artwork Purchases, circa 1977-1998 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Award Certificates, 1996; 1977 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographical Summaries and Curriculum Vitae, circa 1970s-2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bow-tie, circa 1970s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Business and Calling Cards, circa 1940s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Collection Donation to Bass Museum of Art, 1993-1995 (Box 1, Folder 7-9)
  - Donation to Vatican Museums, 2001-2003 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Eric Green Family Documents, circa 1914-1950s (Box 1, Folder 11-12)
  - Guest List for Unidentified Event, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mail Art Exhibition, Museum of Contemporary Art, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Military Dog Tags, circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Military Records, 1942-1947 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Passport, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - School Records, 1930s-1940s (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Travel Itinerary, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Truman Family History, circa 1941-1990s (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Truman Letterhead and Notecards, circa 1970s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Correspondence, 1929-2011; Series 2; 0.6 Linear feet Box 1
  Found here is Truman's personal correspondence with family, friends, artists, and his partner, Eric Green. A small amount of professional correspondence is also included. Of note are postcards and letters from Christo and Jeanne-Claude and artist Leo Rabkin and his wife Dorothy. Handmade holiday cards and a few pieces of mail art sent to Truman are also included.
  - Amundsen, Iver, 1929-1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Archives of American Art, 2004-2007 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - A-B, Miscellaneous, circa 1961-1990s (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Christo and Jeanne-Claude, 1982-1996 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - C-E, Miscellaneous, circa 1960-2007 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Fishbein, Gloria, circa 2010-2011 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - F, Miscellaneous, 1963-2006 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Includes postcards from Helen Frankenthaler.
  - Green, Eric, circa 1967-2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Green, Eric, Correspondence with Others, 1946-1990s (Box 1, Folder 30-31)
  - G-I, Miscellaneous, 1949-1994 (Box 1, Folder 32)
    Includes letters from Grace Glueck.
  - J-L, Miscellaneous, circa 1964-1990 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Mahon, Annette, circa 1950s (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2005-2006 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - M, Miscellaneous, circa 1950s-2007 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - N-O, Miscellaneous, 1974-2004 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Includes a letter from Louise Nevelson.
  - P, Miscellaneous, 1960-2004 (Box 1, Folder 38)
    Includes postcards from Henry Pearson, Betty Parsons, and Lucio Pozzi.
  - Rabkin, Leo and Dorothy, 1971-1998 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Q-S, Miscellaneous, circa 1963-2007 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Truman, Curtis & Mrs. (Parents), circa 1934-1963 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - T-V, Miscellaneous, 1947-1996 (Box 1, Folder 42)
    Includes a handwritten letter from Harry S. Truman.
  - Vollmer, Ruth, 1967-1970s (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - V-Z, Miscellaneous, 1977-2005 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Unidentified, First Names Only, circa 1940s-2000s (Box 1, Folder 45-46)
- Truman Gallery Records, 1975-1979; Series 3; 9 Folders Boxes 2, 6
  The small amount of Truman Gallery records found here include gallery exhibition announcements, news clippings, press releases, and a few photographs of Jock Truman at the gallery. Additionally there are notes and letters from artist Jack Bergamini regarding an exhibition of his work and a folio of cartoons by Ad Reinhardt, published for his exhibition, "Ad Reinhardt: Art Comics and Satires," held at the gallery October 2-30, 1976.
  - Exhibition Announcements, 1975-1979 (Box 2, Folder 1-3)
  - Miscellaneous Records, circa 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - News Clippings, 1976-1979 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Notes and Letters from Jack Bergamini, circa 1976-1978 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs, circa 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Press Releases, circa 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Folio of Cartoons for "Ad Reinhardt: Art Comics and Satires", 1976 (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Writings, circa 1970s-2005; Series 4; 1 Folders Box 2 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Writings by Jock Truman include a few one-page lists and notes as well as brief writings on New Realism, Agnes Martin, and ideas for a television program on collecting.
  - Writings by Jock Truman, circa 1970s-2005 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Printed Material, 1852; 1940s-2010; Series 5; 0.5 Linear feet Boxes 2, 6, OV 7
  Printed material includes exhibition catalogs and announcements, event programs, new clippings, press releases, and travel publications. Also of note are two plastic bags from Keith Haring's original Pop Shop at 292 Lafayette Street in New York.
  - Blank Postcards, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Book, Changing Light by Carol Brockmon, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Brochures and Event Programs, circa 1955-2010 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Exhibition Catalogs and Announcements, circa 1960s-2005 (Box 2, Folder 14-15)
  - Guide to Flowers, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Internet Articles, 2003-2005 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, 1940s-2000 (Box 2, Folder 18-22)
  - Press Releases, circa 1970s (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Reproductions of Artwork and Blank Notecards, undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Travel Brochures, Maps, and Souvenirs, circa 1950s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Gleason's Pictorial Newspaper, 1852 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Keith Haring Pop Shop Bag, 1985 (Box OV 7)
- Artwork, 1860-1995; Series 6; 0.3 Linear feet Boxes 2, 6, OV 7
  Artwork is by Jock Truman and others. Included are handmade holiday cards by Truman and watercolors, pencil, and ink drawings completed by him in the early 1950s. Works by other artists are mostly unidentified but include a few pieces of mail art, sketches, a childhood portrait of Truman, and etchings and woodblock prints.
  - Handmade Holiday Cards, circa 1950s-1960s (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - Pastel Portrait of Jock Truman, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Prints, undated; 1860 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Silhouette Cutouts, 1944 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Miscellaneous Works of Art, circa 1876-1995 (Box 2, Folder 31-33)
  - Oversize Artwork by Jock Truman, 1950s (Box 6, Folder 3)
    Oversize material also housed in OV 7.
  - Oversize Artwork by Jock Truman, from Box 6, Folder 3, 1950s (Box OV 7)
- Photographs, circa 1860s-2009; Series 7; 1.9 Linear feet Boxes 2-6, OV 7
  Photographs are extensive and depict Jock Truman's childhood, family, travel, military service in Brazil, and snapshots of events and social gatherings. Of note are portraits of Truman by Ruth Lazar, photographs of Truman with artists Lyman Kipp and William Congdon, and photographs of Truman at Betty Parsons Gallery. Also found are photographs of Truman with his partner, Eric Green, and many of Green's personal family photographs. Additionally there are inventory photographs of the Jock Truman and Eric Green collection of art.
  - Photographs of Jock Truman, circa 1938-2000s (Box 2, Folder 34-36)
  - Professional Photographs of Jock Truman, 1960s-1970s (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Portraits of Jock Truman by Ruth Lazar, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Photographs of Jock Truman, Lyman Kipp, and William Congdon at Foundry, 1960s (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Jock Truman as a Child, circa 1920-1930 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jock Truman Family Photographs, circa 1860s-1960s (Box 3, Folder 3-4)
  - Photographs of Military Service, Brazil, 1940s (Box 3, Folder 5-7)
  - Photographs of Jock Truman and Eric Green, 1950s-1980s (Box 3, Folder 8-9)
    Oversize material housed in Box 6, Folder 4
  - Photographs of Eric Green, circa 1930s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 10-12)
  - Eric Green Personal and Family Photographs, circa 1900-1940s (Box 3, Folder 13-17)
  - Photographs of Luiz Antonio Velho, circa 1940s (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Portraits of Others, circa early 1900s-1997 (Box 3, Folder 19-20)
  - Miscellaneous Snapshots, 1960s-1990s (Box 3, Folder 21-25)
  - Travel Photographs, circa 1938-1990s (Box 3, Folder 26-31)
  - Travel Negatives, undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Photographs of Mail Art, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of Pont Neuf Wrapped, circa 1985 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Photographs of Art Collection, circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - 2009 Collection Inventory, circa 2005-2009 (Box 4, Folder 5-6)
  - "Works we no longer own", circa 1990s (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Negatives, circa 1980s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Slides of Brazil, undated (Box 5, Folder 1-3)
  - Oversize Photograph of Jock Truman and Eric Green, from Box 3, Folder 9, 1985 (Box 6, Folder 4)